Finding Aid to the Families collection SSC.MS.00391
Sophia Smith Collection
Families collection
1853-1980
1930-1980
Sophia Smith Collection
SSC.MS.00391
5 boxes (3 linear feet)
Collection contains articles, bibliographies, books, greeting cards, leaflets, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, periodicals, reports, and syllabi addressing "the family," including topics such as homemakers, housework, marriage, unwed mothers, and divorce. Includes feminist critique of marriage and the family by both well-known feminists and more mainstream writers and journalists. Contains documentation of the changes in American family structures and norms that resulted from the cultural and socio-economic changes of the 1960s and 1970s.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Unknown source. Accession numbers: no accession number, 93S-1, 09S-68. Accessions were received on the following dates: ?-1993, 2009-08-10.
Other Finding Aids
OCLC Number: 49517091
Scope and Contents
The Families collection contains articles, bibliographies, books, greeting cards, leaflets, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, periodicals, reports, and syllabi addressing a range of topics subsumed under "the family" including homemakers, housework, marriage, unwed mothers, and divorce. The material spans the period from 1853-1980. There are a few documents from the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, including Charlotte Perkins Gilman's 1907 article on motherhood and a 1928 article entitled "Yashee: Motherhood and Babyhood in Soviet Russia." These items reflect the prevailing attitudes of those decades by defining marriage and motherhood as the normal and desirable goals for all women, and defining those who did not pursue marriage and motherhood as maladjusted.
The majority of the items date from the years 1960-80. Many of these documents--such as Marvin Sussman's study, The Capacity of U.S. Families in the 1970s to Provide an Appropriate Child-rearing Environment (1973) and the booklet, Eleven Million Teenagers: What Can Be Done about the Epidemic of Adolescent Pregnancies (1976) --reflect the middle-class liberal concerns and anxieties that emerged from national social programs like the Great Society and the War on Poverty. A great deal of this material presents the feminist critique of marriage and the family as it was articulated by both well known feminists and more mainstream writers and journalists. The collection contains documentation of the changes in American family structures and norms that resulted from the cultural and socio-economic changes that took place during the 1960s and 1970s. It also demonstrates the presence of a small but vocal minority of women who joined organizations such as the Martha Movement to protest women's movement away from traditional definitions of housewife and mother.
Marriage--History--Sources; Motherhood--History--Sources; Family--History--Sources; Eugenics--History--Sources; Child rearing--History--Sources; Displaced homemakers--History--Sources; Divorce--History--Sources; Divorced mothers--History--Sources; Housewives--History--Sources; Househusbands--History--Sources; Feminism--History--United States--Sources; Married women--History--Sources; Marriage counseling--United States--History--Sources; Sterilization (birth control)--History--Sources; Teenage pregnancy--United States--History--Sources; Weddings--History--Sources; Women--Psychology--History--Sources; Working mothers--United States--History--Sources; Gilman, Charlotte Perkins, 1860-1935; Homemakers; Wives; Mothers; Feminists; clippings; Pamphlets; reports; Newsletters; articles; Books; Bibliographies; Leaflets; syllabi; Greeting cards; National Organization for Women--History; Sophia Smith Collection
- Bibliographies, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Children, 1979; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Economics, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Feminist perspectives, 1970-79 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Homemakers
  - General, 1967-77; undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Displaced homemakers, 1979-83; undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Housework, 1972-80; undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  General
  [See also Jarrett Box 4 for housekeeping aids,WPA photographs, 1938]
- Marriage, divorce, and desertion
  - Printed material
    - 1853-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - 1899-1990s, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Legal matters, 1973-84; undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, 1974-77 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1970s; undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Real Women, Real Lives, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Women as wives, 1895-1979; undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Motherhood
  - General, 1899-1970s; undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mother at Home, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1895-1970s; undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Unwed mothers, 1970s; undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- White House Conference on Families, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Women's Conference, audio recordings, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous, 1969-79 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Baby book kept by Jeanette Hellman Gerber for her two sons, David Allison and Kenneth Edward Gerber, 1944-1950 (Box 4)
- Books on shelf:
  - Astell, Mary, Some Reflections upon Marriage, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Carter, Mary Elizabeth, House and Home, 1904 (Box 5)
  - Chavasse, Pye Henry, M.D., Wife and Mother, 1888 (Box 5)
  - Child, Lydia Maria, The Frugal Housewife, 1830 (Box 5)
  - Dike, Rev. Samuel W., Special Issues of the National League for the Protection of the Family for 1909 (Box 5)
  - Dike, Rev. Samuel W., Some Fundamentals of the Divorce Question, 1909 (Box 5)
  - Gilman, Charlotte Perkins, Concerning Children, 1900 (Box 5)
  - Kerber, Judith, Families, 1978
  - Look, special issue on "The American Family,", January 26, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Longshore-Potts, Anna M., Love, Courtship, and Marriage, 1891 (Box 5)
  - Miles, Alfred H., ed., The Household Oracle, 1898 (Box 5)
  - Parkes, Mrs. William, Domestic Duties, 1829 (Box 5)
  - Pierson, Emma Belle D., When Things Go Wrong: A Harried Housewife's Helper, 1912 (Box 5)
  - Sangster, Margaret, The Queenly Mother, 1907 (Box 5)
  - Smith, Stevenson, Madge W. Wilkinson, and Louisa C. Wagoner, Summary of the Laws of Several States Governing Marriage and Divorce of the Feebleminded..., 1914 (Box 5)
  - Soyer, Alexis, The Modern Housewife or Ménagerè, 1849 (Box 5)
  - Van de Velde, T.H., Sex Hostility in Marriage, 1931 (Box 5)
  - White House Conference, 1930: Addresses and Abstracts of Committee Reports of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, called by President Herbert Hoover, 1931 (Box 5)